Guide to the Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives Moving Images Collection FILMS.001
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
- Series I: Transport Workers Union of America, 1930-1967
  Most materials in this series focus on Local 100, the TWU's New York City local representing bus and subway workers, but also included are segments concerning the international union and its Railroad and Air Transport divisions, as well as Locals 101 (Brooklyn Union Gas utility workers) and 234 (Philadelphia transit workers). They are drawn from the following materials, all produced by or for the union: seven documentaries, United We Are Invincible(1941); Our Case For The Forty-Hour Week(1950), The Transport Workers Union of America, CIO, Presents Proceedings Of Its Seventh Biennial Convention(1950), Memorial Tribute To Mr. CIO—Allan S. Haywood(1953); Twenty-Nine Days To Victory(1953), Years Of Challenge(1961), and The Best Is Yet To Come(1967), as well as programs, press conferences, and filmed press releases broadcast on television (including national conventions and locals' mass meetings, officers' reports to locals and national divisions, and reports to the public on its actions). The largest number of segments consist outtakes from the completed films and television program, as well as unedited footage.
  The films in this series include many hours of footage of the TWU's ebullient, truculent, theatrical and colorful long-time president, Michael J. Quill. These present a visual record of his life and career, from young and sprightly in the 1930s (including a rally during his successful 1939 campaign to be elected to the New York City Council) to aging and ill, being jailed during the disastrous 1966 New York City transit strike, and, only weeks later, his funeral cortege emerging from New York City's St. Patrick's Cathedral, and including glimpses of his family, his son, John Quill, as well as his wives, Mollie (O'Neill) Quill and Shirley (Garry) Quill. Quill's fiery oratory, sharp tongue, shrewd wit, and agile repartee is on display here, including his trademark threat, that the union would stay on the picket line "until the plains of hell itself freeze over"; his calling one of New York City's mayors "a plain, ordinary, common liar"; and many instances of his rhetorically skewering his opponents (in management, in politics, and within his own union) in person and in the media. The series also includes other TWU officers and staff, including: Eugene Attreed, Gustav Faber, Maurice Forge, Daniel Gilmartin, William Grogan, Matthew Guinan, Austin Hogan, James Horst, Andrew Kaelin, Mark Kavanaugh, Matthew Kearns, Douglas MacMahon, Frank O'Connor, John O'Donnell, Harry Sacher, John Santo, James Shannon, Frank Sheehan, and Ellis Van Riper.
  TWU footage also includes prominent leaders of other unions and national labor organizations, such as the CIO's John L. Lewis, Philip Murray and Allan Haywood, the AFL-CIO's George Meany, Joseph Curran of the National Maritime Union, David J. MacDonald of the United Steel Workers, and the International Brotherhood of Teamsters' James R. Hoffa (who can be seen promising not to raid TWU locals); officials of New York City and State AFL-CIO councils, including Raymond Diana, Louis Hollander, Morris Iushewitz, Martin Lacey, and Harry Van Arsdale, Jr. Other labor-related figures represented include Arthur Goldberg, a labor lawyer whose clients included the TWU before he became United States Secretary of Labor and later a United States Supreme Court Justice; noted labor arbitrator, Theodore Kheel; labor negotiator, Julius Manson and "labor priest," Father Charles Owen Rice of Pittsburgh. Politicians and officials are represented, too: New York City mayors Fiorello LaGuardia and Robert F. Wagner, Jr.; New York City Transit Authority commissioners John J. Gilhooley and Joseph E. O' Grady, and Philadelphia mayors Joseph S. Clark, Jr., Richardson Dilworth, and James Hugh Joseph Tate. Also worth noting are persons who are not on-screen, but are mentioned, usually with invective. Rudolph Halley, president of the New York City Council, New York City mayor Vincent Impellitteri, New York City Comptroller Lawrence E. Gerosa, New York State governor Thomas E. Dewey, and anti-union, anti-communist lawyer Roy Cohn, all get their share of this treatment.
  Other footage includes mass meetings, rallies, demonstrations, Labor Day parades (which document other unions' contingents as well as the TWU's), contract negotiations, press conferences, picket lines, strikes, and speeches, beginning with the early days of the TWU in the 1930s and 1940s (including its attendance at a 1943 national CIO convention); TWU participation in World War II "United Front" activities such as a huge 1942 "Defend America" rally, with US and Soviet flags side by side on the podium and buses bearing slogans like, "Uncle Sam Won't Miss the Bus—Lick Hitler in 1942; and the expulsion of Communist Party members from the union six years later. Also shown are members at work: bus drivers, subway conductors and motormen, utility workers, baggage handlers and airplane maintenance mechanics, flight attendants, railroad train maintenance workers, and gas utility workers. The ethnic makeup of TWU's officers and members, many of them of Irish extraction, is reflected in footage of TWU officers and members participating in New York City's annual St. Patrick's Day parade; footage of members and officers of other ethnic groups, including African-American officers such as Herman C. Gray, Louis Manning, Edward T. Williamson, and rank and file members in the audience at mass meetings.
  Also among these materials are: a long speech given by Michael Quill at the union's 30th anniversary meeting in 1964, in which he discusses the TWU's and his relationship with the Communist Party, as well as what may be the earliest footage of an attempted corporate takeover and proxy fight, as Quill and the TWU went toe-to-toe over the management of the Fifth Avenue Bus Company – represented by Lawrence Weissman, Harry Weinberg, and Roy Cohn -- in 1962. (This sequence includes candid footage in which some participants are clearly not aware of being filmed.) And while there is no footage directly showing dissidents against the TWU's entrenched leadership, documentation of these groups and individuals is not entirely absent. It is manifested in Quill's shouting down union dissidents from the podium, in his direct as well as oblique (uncomplimentary) references to them at mass meetings, and in his testy response to questions from reporters about wildcat strikes within the union; and it can be heard in occasional catcalls from the TWU convention floor.
  The series also includes informal and candid scenes of working-class social life of the 1940s and 50s, for example, color footage of union officers and members with spouses and children, dressed in their Sunday best, attending an annual "Field Day" in Croke Park in the Bronx; the union's "11th annual outing," replete with drum and bagpipe bands, pony rides, clowns, hotdogs, beer, ice cream, and competitive athletic events such as softball, soccer, high jump, horse shoes, shot put, foot races; footage of a racially integrated holiday party showing adults smoking and drinking; and a banquet celebration.
  - Tape 1, cuid36982 (Box 33)
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
    Duration: 25 minutes
  - Transport Workers Union members leafleting on street at parade; parade. Footage; B/W; Silent. Running Time: 2:21., 1930-1949; cuid8017 (Item T 1-H 3)
  - Transport Workers Union bus drivers; Transport Workers Union's Transport Hall; Philip Murray negotiates with New York City mayor? New York, NY; City Hall, New York, NY; Transport Hall, New York, NY. Footage; B/W; Silent. Running Time: 2:35., 1930-1949; cuid8018 (Item T 1-H 4)
  - Transport Workers Union rally at City Hall. New York, NY. Footage; B/W; Silent. Running Time: 2:23., 1930-1939; cuid8019 (Item T 1-H 5)
  - Exterior of bus company garage; 1930s street scenes in New York City boroughs; Transport Workers Union elections? New York, NY; Jamaica, Queens, New York, NY. Footage; B/W; Silent. Running Time: 4:40., 1930-1939; cuid8015 (Item T 1-H 1)
  - Early demonstration by Transport Workers Union; early footage of some of union's founding member leaders speaking at a rally. New York, NY. Footage; B/W; Silent. Running Time: 5:45., 1935-1939; cuid36981 (Item T 1-H 2)
  - Tape 2, cuid914 (Box 28)
    This tape contains T 2-H-6, T 2-H-7
    Format: BetacamSP, Estimated Duration: 00:59:35, BW
  - Transport Workers Union members picket the homes of more than a dozen individual TWU members (in different locations) who have "deserted" the union; Michael Quill and other union leaders speaking at outdoor rallies. New York, NY. Footage; B/W; Silent. Running Time: 13:09., 1940-1941; cuid915 (Item T 2-H 7)
    A digitized copy of this film is available on tape 2.
  - Rally for Michael Quill's re-election to New York City Council; Third Biennial Convention of the Transport Workers Union; Transport Workers Union and pro-World War II demonstrations; field days and outings of the Transport Workers Union's members and families. New York, NY; Fifth Avenue, New York, NY; Croke Park, New York, NY; New York Public Library, New York, NY. Footage; Color and B/W; Silent. Running Time: 44:42., 1930-1949; cuid1022 (Item T 2-H 6)
  - Tape 3, cuid1024 (Box 33, Item 3)
    This tape contains T 3-H-8, T 3-H-9, T 3-H-10, T 3-H-11, T 3-H-12, T 3-H-13, T 3-H-14, T 3-H-15T 3-H-7
    Format: BetacamSP, Estimated Duration: 01:00:35, BW
  - Transport Workers Union strikers' picket line. Transport Workers Union pickets home of an ex-member. New York, Bronx? Footage; B/W; Silent. Running Time: 2:54., 1940-1941; cuid1023 (Item T 3-H 8)
    A digitized copy of this film is available on tape 3.
  - Transport Workers Union pickets home of TWU member accused of "deserting" the union. New York, NY. Footage; B/W; Silent. Running Time: 2:50., 1940-1941; cuid8020 (Item T 3-H 9)
  - Airplane maintenance; airplane baggage; flight crew and United We Are Invincible (documentary on the Transport Workers Union's 1941 strike against the New York City Omnibus Corporation and Fifth Avenue Coach Company). New York, NY. Footage and nearly complete film; Color and B/W; Sound. Running Time: 30:28., 1941, 1960-1969; cuid8021 (Item T 3-H 10)
  - Bus drivers' occupational maladies; Transport Workers Union strike meeting. New York, NY. Part of complete film; B/W; Sound. Running Time: 6:35., 1941; cuid8022 (Item T 3-H 11)
  - Bus-driving, bus passengers, and traffic in New York City. New York, NY. Footage; B/W; Sound. Running Time: 4:38., 1941; cuid8023 (Item T 3-H 12)
  - CIO Convention. Philadelphia, PA?. Footage; B/W; Silent. Running Time: 2:55., 1943; cuid8024 (Item T 3-H 13)
  - Transport Workers Union Local 100 delegates departing New York City for TWU 6th Biennial Convention. New York, NY. Footage; B/W; Silent. Running Time: 2:56., Dec 1948; cuid8025 (Item T 3-H 14)
  - Michael Quill and his young son, John, at a Transport Workers Union convention - possibly the 6th Biennial Convention. Chicago, IL? Footage; B/W; Silent. Running Time: 2:55., Dec 1948; cuid8026 (Item T 3-H 15)
  - Tape 4, cuid36983 (Box 33)
    Duration: 23 minutes
  - Transport Workers Union officers, staff, (and families?) at a banquet/celebration, possibly at union's 6th Biennial Convention. Chicago, IL ? Footage; B/W; Silent. Running Time: 2:50., Dec 1948; cuid8027 (Item T 4-H 16)
  - Scenes from Transport Workers Union's 6th Biennial Convention. Chicago, IL; Lake Michigan, Chicago, IL. Footage; B/W; Silent. Running Time: 3:00., Dec 1948; cuid8028 (Item T 4-H 17)
  - Demonstration; Fiorello LaGuardia and Michael Quill speaking at a rally. New York, NY; Union Square?, New York, NY. Footage; B/W; Silent. Running Time: 1:30., 1940-1945; cuid8029 (Item T 4-H 18)
  - Demonstrations, picket lines, rallies of Transport Workers Union urging New York City's Board of Transportation to implement collective bargaining. New York, NY; Hudson Street, New York, NY. Footage; B/W; Silent. Running Time: 13:22., 1940-1949; cuid8030 (Item T 4-H 19)
  - Tape 5, cuid36984 (Box 33)
    Duration: 46 minutes
  - Our Case For The Forty-Hour Week. (Part of?) a documentary on the Transport Workers Union's drive to win a forty hour week for New York City Board of Transportation employees. Brooklyn, NY; New York, NY; City Hall, New York, NY; New York City Board of Transportation headquarters, Brooklyn, NY; Johnson Street, Brooklyn, NY. Footage; part of complete film?; B/W; Silent. Running Time: 44:25., 1950; cuid8031 (Item T 5-H 20)
  - Tape 6, cuid36985 (Box 33)
    Duration: 49 minutes
  - The Transport Workers Union Of America, CIO, Presents Proceedings Of Its Seventh Biennial Convention. New York, NY; Transport Hall, New York, NY. Completed film; B/W; Silent. Running Time: 40:15., Dec 6, 1950 -Dec 9, 1950; cuid8032 (Item T 6-H 21)
  - Transport Workers Union Local 100 members voting. New York, NY. Footage; B/W; Silent. Running Time: 7:10., Jul 6, 1951; cuid8033 (Item T 6-H 22)
  - Tape 7, cuid36986 (Box 33)
    Duration: 44 minutes
  - Contract negotiations between Transport Workers Union and New York City private bus lines. New York, NY. Rough edit of a partially-completed film?; B/W; Silent. Running Time: 42:35., 1951; cuid8034 (Item T 7-H 23)
  - Tape 8, cuid36987 (Box 33)
    Duration: 61 minutes
  - Television program (kinescope) relating to Transport Workers Union's 1952 convention. Philadelphia, PA. Footage; B/W; Sound; Silent. Running Time: 20:08., cuid8035 (Item T 8-H 0)
  - Memorial meeting for Philip Murray. New York, NY. Footage; B/W; Sound. Running Time: 16:10., 1952; cuid8036 (Item T 8-H 1)
  - Twenty-Nine Days To Victory. Documentary chronicling 1953 strike of the Transport Workers Union Local 100 against nine privately-owned New York City bus lines. New York, NY; St. Nicholas Arena, New York, NY; Times Square, New York, NY. Complete film; B/W; Sound. Running Time: 23:25., cuid8037 (Item T 8-H 2)
  - Tape 9, cuid36988 (Box 33)
    Duration: 50 minutes
  - Michael Quill and Matthew Guinan at a Transport Workers Union mass meeting on the eve of the 1953 private bus lines strike in New York City; Quill and Allan Haywood address mass strike meeting. New York, NY. Footage; B/W; Sound. Running Time: 15:20., Dec 31, 1952, 1953; cuid8038 (Item T 9-H 3)
  - Rank and file members of Transport Workers Union at a union meeting; Allan Haywood and Michael Quill addressing mass meeting (s?); workers going on and coming off shifts and at work. New York, NY. Footage. B/W; Sound; Silent. Running Time: 17:42., 1950-1959; cuid8039 (Item T 9-H 4)
  - Filmed press release: Michael Quill announces a meeting of striking bus workers. New York, NY. Footage; B/W; Sound; Silent. Running Time: 3:42., 1953; cuid8040 (Item T 9-H 5)
  - Allan Haywood of the CIO speaks in support of New York City bus strike and need for 40-hour week for New York City and Philadelphia bus drivers. New York, NY. Footage; B/W; Sound. Running Time: 5:45., 1953; cuid8042 (Item T 9-H 7)
  - Father Charles Owen Rice making a statement of support for a Transport Workers Union strike. New York, NY. Footage; B/W; Sound. Running Time: 3:40., 1953; cuid8041 (Item T 9-H 6)
  - Tape 10, cuid36989 (Box 34)
    Duration: 53 minutes
  - Officers of the Transport Workers Union (and friends) report on the progress of the 1953 strike against New York City private bus lines. New York, NY. Footage; B/W; Sound. Running Time: 19:10., cuid8043 (Item T 10-H 8)
  - Michael Quill addressing two different mass meetings during Transport Workers Union's 1953 strike against New York City private bus lines. New York, NY. Footage; B/W; Sound. Running Time: 20:04., cuid8044 (Item T 10-H 9)
  - Transport Workers Union's Michael Quill addresses mass meeting of strikers during 1953 strike against private bus lines in New York City. New York, NY. Footage; B/W; Sound. Running Time: 10:35., cuid8045 (Item T 10-H 10)
  - Tape 11, cuid36990 (Box 33)
    Durartion: 52 minutes
  - Mass meeting of strikers during Transport Workers Union's 1953 strike against New York City private bus lines. New York, NY. Footage; B/W; Sound. Running Time: 32:12., cuid8046 (Item T 11-H 11)
  - Mass meeting of strikers during Transport Workers Union Local 100's 1953 strike against New York City's private bus lines. New York, NY. Footage; B/W; Sound. Running Time: 11:00., cuid8047 (Item T 11-H 12)
  - Crowded subway station and subway station entrances. New York, NY. Footage; B/W; Sound; Silent. Running Time: 6:06., 1953; cuid8048 (Item T 11-H 13)
  - Tape 12, cuid36991 (Box 33)
    Durartion: 43 minutes
  - Memorial Tribute To Mr. CIO—Allan S. Haywood. 1952, New York, NY. Complete film; B/W; Sound. Running Time: 10:45., 1952, 1953; cuid8049 (Item T 12-H 14)
  - Matthew Guinan, Ellis Van Riper, John O'Donnell and Michael Quill report to mass meeting of Transport Workers Union Local 100 members on relations with the newly-created New York City Transit Authority and Transport Workers Union's program for working conditions and wages. New York, NY; Manhattan Center auditorium, New York, NY. Complete television program; B/W; Sound. Running Time: 30:05., Oct 7, 1953; cuid8050 (Item T 12-H 15)
  - Tape 13, cuid1025 (Box 33, Item 13)
    This tape contains T 3-H 16, T 3-H-17, T 3-H 18
    Format: BetacamSP, Estimated Duration: 00:51:25, BW
  - Last official meeting Transport Workers Union held in its old headquarters. Commemorates the union's history and salutes the opening of its new headquarters. (Part 1) New York, NY; Transport Hall, New York, NY. Footage; B/W; Sound. Running Time: 25:16., Dec 1953; cuid8051 (Item T 13-H 16)
    A digitized copy of this film is available on tape 13.
  - Last official meeting Transport Workers Union held in its old headquarters. Commemorates the union's history and salutes the opening of its new headquarters. (Part 2) New York, NY; Transport Hall, New York, NY. Footage; B/W; Sound; Silent. Running Time: 24:28., Dec 1953; cuid8052 (Item T 13-H 17)
  - Transport Workers Union members voting in a Transport Workers Union election or on contract or strike settlement. New York, NY; Cassidy's Restaurant, New York, NY. Footage; B/W; Silent. Running Time: 5:46., 1953; cuid8053 (Item T 13-H 18)
  - Tape 14, cuid1026 (Box 33, Item 14)
    This tape contains T 14-H 19, T 14-H 20, T 14-H 21, T 14-H 22, T 2-H-7
    Format: BetacamSP, Estimated Duration: 01:02:00, BW
  - Michael Quill attempts to bring a Transport Workers Union meeting to order, and speaks. New York, NY. Footage; B/W; Sound. Running Time: 5:16., 1953, 1962; cuid8054 (Item T 14-H 19)
    A digitized copy of this film is available on tape 14.
  - Michael Quill makes a statement addressed to the general public endorsing the candidacy of Robert F. Wagner, Jr. for mayor of New York. New York, NY. Footage; B/W; Sound. Running Time: 5:26., 1953; cuid8055 (Item T 14-H 20)
  - Exteriors of co-op apartment buildings, New York City school; footage relating to Robert F. Wagner, Jr.'s mayoral election campaign; Michael Quill addressing mass meeting of Local 100 members on strike. New York, NY. Footage; B/W; Sound; Silent. Running Time: 17:30., 1953; cuid8056 (Item T 14-H 21)
  - The 20th Anniversary Celebration of the Transport Workers Union - Part 1. New York, NY; St. Nicholas Arena, New York, NY. Complete television program; B/W; Sound. Running Time: 31:21., Apr 29, 1954; cuid8057 (Item T 14-H 22)
  - Tape 15, cuid36992 (Box 34)
    Duration: 57 minutes
  - The 20th Anniversary Celebration of the Transport Workers Union – Part 2., New York, NY; St. Nicholas Arena (New York, NY). Complete television program; B/W; Sound. Running Time: 30:30., Apr 29, 1954; cuid8058 (Item T 15-H 23)
  - Two press conferences with Michael Quill speaking; passengers on New York City subway trains and buses, ca. 1950s; Transport Workers Union's Twentieth Anniversary Meeting, 1954. New York, NY; St. Nicholas Arena, New York, NY. Footage; B/W; Sound; Silent. Running Time: 23:52., 1950-1959; cuid8059 (Item T 15-H 0)
  - Tape 16, cuid36993 (Box 34)
    Duration: 63 minutes
  - Transport Workers Union demonstration to save the Third Avenue elevated subway line in New York City. New York, NY. Footage; B/W; Silent. Running Time: 8:30., 1954-1955; cuid8060 (Item T 16-H 1)
  - Picket line, demonstration by Transport Workers Union to "Save the 3rd Avenue El" (protesting destruction of elevated subway line.) New York, NY. Footage; B/W; Silent. Running Time: 9:45., 1954-1955; cuid8061 (Item T 16-H 2)
  - Officers of Transport Workers Union Local 234 and Michael Quill urge local members to ratify new contract with Philadelphia Transportation Company. Philadelphia, PA ? Footage; B/W; Sound; Silent. Running Time: 14:08., Feb 1956-Mar 1956; cuid8062 (Item T 16-H 3)
  - Partial print of the Transport Workers Union's A Memorial Tribute To Philip Murray. Scotland. Parts of a complete film (kinescope); B/W; Sound. Running Time: 27:42., Nov 13, 1957; cuid8063 (Item T 16-H 4)
  - Tape 17, cuid1027 (Box 28, Item 17)
    This tape contains T 17-H 5, T 17-H 6, T 17-H 7, T 17-H 8, T 17-H 9, T 17-H 10, T 17-H 11, T 7-H 12, T 17-H 13
    Format: BetacamSP, Estimated Duration: 01:03:22, BW
  - Pieces of Transport Workers Union's A Memorial Tribute To Philip Murray; trims from newsreel footage of Murray; Murray's funeral? Various locations. Footage; B/W; Sound; Silent. Running Time: 11:53., 1940-1959; cuid8064 (Item T 17-H 5)
    A digitized copy of this film is available on tape 17.
  - Michael Quill statement on progress of American labor. VO by a narrator talking about the life of Philip Murray. Various locations. Footage; B/W; Sound. Running Time: 1:35., Nov 13, 1957; cuid8065 (Item T 17-H 6)
  - Transport Workers Union's Michael Quill demands that the New York City Transit Authority conduct a representation election among its employees. New York, NY. Filmed press release; B/W; Sound. Running Time: 00:50., Sep 17, 1957; cuid8066 (Item T 17-H 7)
  - Voters in Transport Workers Union (representation?) election. New York, NY. Footage; B/W; Silent. Running Time: 1:25., Dec 16, 1957; cuid8067 (Item T 17-H 8)
  - Transport Workers Union Local 100 members vote to authorize a strike against private bus lines in the New York City metropolitan area. New York, NY; Manhattan Center (auditorium), New York, NY. Footage; B/W; Sound; Silent. Running Time: 9:10., Dec 1957; cuid8068 (Item T 17-H 9)
  - Transport Workers Union demonstration and automobile cavalcade against the Pennsylvania Railroad. Altoona, PA; Harrisburg ?, PA. Footage; B/W; Silent. Running Time: 4:35., 1957; cuid8069 (Item T 17-H 10)
  - Transport Workers Union officials present the union's complaints against the management of the Pennsylvania Railroad to a meeting of presidents of 51 Railroad Division locals. New York, NY; Hotel Park Sheraton, New York, NY. Complete television program; B/W; Sound. Running Time: 14:20., 1957-1958; cuid8070 (Item T 17-H 11)
  - Transport Workers Union's Michael Quill reacts to an indictment that appears to have been handed down against either the Transport Workers Union or Quill himself by a Brooklyn Grand Jury. New York, NY; Bar Association Building, New York, NY. Footage; B/W; Sound; Silent. Running Time: 7:50., 1950-1959; cuid8071 (Item T 17-H 12)
  - Mass meeting of Local 100 Transport Workers Union; strike resolution. New York, NY; Manhattan Center auditorium, New York, NY. Footage; B/W; Sound. Running Time: 6:30., Dec 27, 1959; cuid8072 (Item T 17-H 13)
  - Tape 18, cuid36994 (Box 34)
  - Harry Van Arsdale, Jr. addresses mass meeting of Transport Workers Union Local 100. New York, NY; Manhattan Center auditorium, New York, NY. Footage; B/W; Sound. Running Time: 2:00., Dec 27, 1959; cuid8073 (Item T 18-H 14)